A Guide to the René Jules Dubos papers, Rockefeller University Faculty FA122
Rockefeller Archive Center
- (CONFERENCES AND LECTURES)
  - Sermon, The Church of the Epiphany, New York, 1974 February 4 (Box 118, Folder 22)
  - Klopsteg Lecture, "Man Made Environments: The Symbiosis Between Man and Nature", Northwestern University, 1974 April 16 (Box 118, Folder 22)
  - Third Pacific Architectural Conference, The American Institute of Architects, Calif. Council, 1974 October 26-31 (Box 118, Folder 22)
  - National Town Meeting, "The Late Great Planet Earth", John F. Kennedy Center for the Performing Arts, 1974 December 19 (Box 118, Folder 22)
  - World Business Council Winter Conference, Education Session VI: "Choices That Make Us Human", Ocean Reef Club, Key Largo, Florida, 1975 January 26-30 (Box 118, Folder 23)
  - A Conference on the Environment and Human Needs, Spaceship Earth, "People Need What They Want: From Nature to Resources", Yale University, 1975 February 12-14 (Box 118, Folder 23)
  - Visiting Scholar Program, "Man-made Resources and Environments", Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, 1975 February 18-19 (Box 118, Folder 23)
  - OCTO [Octogenarians], "Celebration of Life", to Celebrate the Opening of the Yorkville Luncheon Club, 1975 April 9 (Box 118, Folder 23)
  - Adventures in Ideas, Keen College of New Jersey, Spring Building A Human Future, "Strategies for World Future", Seton Hall University, 1975 June 26 (Box 118, Folder 23)
  - Lecture, "Societal Implications of a Steady State Population", Bard College, 1975 September 26-27 (Box 118, Folder 23)
  - Symposium, "Life: It's Origins and Future" [text], sponsored by St. John's University, 1975 May (Box 118, Folder 24)
  - Bicentennial Celebration, Keynote Address, 1975 May 22 (Box 118, Folder 25)
- (CONFERENCES AND LECTURES), 1975
  - Lecture, The National Meeting of the Bicentennial Seniors, Colonial Williamsburg, January 16-19, 1976 (Box 119, Folder 1)
  - Ways of Healing: Ancient and Modern, "Ecological Views of Health", The University of Calif. San Francisco, January 24-25, 1976 (Box 119, Folder 1)
  - Scenic Hudson Preservation Conference, "Wind Energy Now", The Cosmopolitan Club, NYC, March 1, 1976 (Box 119, Folder 1)
  - Silver Jubilee Annual Mendel Lecture, "Creative Adaptions to the Future," Saint Peter's College, March 9, 1976 (Box 119, Folder 1)
  - The Rockefeller University Lecture, "Symbiosis Between Humankind and the Earth", May 14, 1976 (Box 119, Folder 1)
  - Colloque Interdisciplinaire sur la Santé, Pour un Nouveau Contrat Medical, "Le Santé, Problème Humain", [Health, the Human Problem] Montreal, College Ahuntsic, June 3, 1976 (Box 119, Folder 1)
  - A Celebration To Life: Aspect II, "Modern Medicine and the Quality of Life", Mount Sinai Medical Center, Milwaukee, WI, June 5, 1976 (Box 119, Folder 1)
  - Tyler Ecology Award Symposium, sponsored by Pepperdine University, April 9, 1976 (Box 119, Folder 2)
  - Center for Bioethics, Clinical Research Institute of Montreal, 1976 (Box 119, Folder 3)
  - Lecture, Boulder Colorado [unidentified], itinerary, January 23-25, 1977 (Box 119, Folder 4)
  - Biomedical lecture, "Creative Adaptations", University of Calif. San Diego, March 3, 1977 (Box 119, Folder 4)
  - Society of Medical Psychoanalysts Scientific Meetings, Annual Academic Lecture, "Happiness vs Joie de Vivre", New York City, April 27, 1977 (Box 119, Folder 4)
  - Mann Ranch Seminars, [catalog], René Dubos Lecture, "Continuous Creation Through Symbiosis Between Humankind and the Earth", Ukiah, CA, July 8-10, 1977 (Box 119, Folder 4)
  - Tenth Anniversary Observance, The Pennsylvania State University, College of Human Developments, "Environment, Choices and Human Development", October 9-14, 1977 (Box 119, Folder 4)
  - Nobel Dinner, Panel Discussion [Adolphus College ?], October 5, 1977 (Box 119, Folder 4)
  - Seventeenth Interscience Conference on Antimicrobial Agents and Chemotherapy, sponsored by the American Society for Microbiology, New York, October 12-14, 1977 (Box 119, Folder 4)
  - The 6th Annual Saint Peter's College Business Symposium, "Creative Planning for the Future", November 1, 1977 (Box 119, Folder 4)
  - Cosmopolitan Club, "Energy: What Are Our Alternative Choices?", December 5, 1977 (Box 119, Folder 4)
  - A Series of Leaky Foundation Lectures, L.S.B. Leakey Foundation, "Improving on Nature", February 1, 1977 (Box 119, Folder 4)
  - Danz Lecture, University of Washington, March 27-April 14, 1978 (Box 119, Folder 5)
  - The Caldwell B. Esselstyn Fellowship, "Health and the Spirit of Man", Yale University, April 19-21, 1978 (Box 119, Folder 5)
  - Human Ecology: A Weekend Symposium, "Symbiosis of Earth and Humankind", Sponsored by The American University, May 6-7, 1978 (Box 119, Folder 5)
  - Aldo Leopold Memorial Colloquium, "Humankind and Land", University of Wisconsin-Madison, June 21, 1978 (Box 119, Folder 5)
  - The Warner Foundation Series, "Wooing of the Earth", College of St. Scholastica, MN, October 3-4, 1978 (Box 119, Folder 5)
  - Bard College Center, Inaugural Program, "The Wooing of the Earth", October 15, 1978 (Box 119, Folder 5)
  - Theodore Brameld Lecture and 8th Annual Society for Educational Reconstruction [SER] Conference, "Thinking Globally, Acting Locally", Fordham University, October 21, 1978 (Box 119, Folder 5)
  - The Rockefeller University, Research Colloquium 35th Anniversary of the JEM Paper by Avery McLeod and McCarty, February 2, 1979 (Box 119, Folder 6)
  - Threshold Foundation, "Towards One Reality", 1979 (Box 119, Folder 6)
  - Second D'Arros Conference, participants and agenda, 1979 (Box 119, Folder 6)
  - World Game '79, "Strategies For Feeding Humanity", New York University, July 14-21, 1979 (Box 119, Folder 6)
  - The Earth's Sacred Voyage, "The Wooing of the Earth", The Cathedral of Saint John the Divine, October 28, 1979 (Box 119, Folder 6)
  - Dixième Colloque De la Pharmacie Hospitaliere, L'Institute des Sciences de la Santé, [Paris] March 21-22, 1980 (Box 119, Folder 7)
  - Energy and the Way We Live, "Finding the Path to an Uncertain Future", Dutchess Community College, April 20, 1980 (Box 119, Folder 7)
  - The American Academy of Arts and Sciences, May, 1980 (Box 119, Folder 7)
  - Congrès national de la protection des plantes", 1980 (Box 119, Folder 7)
  - Cultures - Protection De L'Environnement", [Protection of Cultures - Protection of the Environment] Deauville, May 28-29, 1980 (Box 119, Folder 7)
  - Samuel R, Milbank Lecture in Health and Society, "Human Meanings of Health", Barnard College, 1980 (Box 119, Folder 7)
  - Symposium, Medicine and Religion, "Human Being vs Homo Sapiens", Medical Society of the State of New York, October 19, 1980 (Box 119, Folder 7)
  - Troiseimes Assises Internationales de L'Enivronnement, "L'Adaptation de L'Homme à son Environnement", [The Adaption of Man to His Environment] December 9-1, 1980 (Box 119, Folder 8)
  - Conference on the Destination of Human Beings, Roper Poll, May, 1981 (Box 119, Folder 9)
  - Colloque Sur Les Peurs Du 20eme Siècle, [Colloquium on the Fears of the 20th Century. In French] February 17, 1981 (Box 119, Folder 9)
  - Saturday at the University, Social Imperatives and the Development of Science, Technology and Medicine, "Human Concerns and Medical Research", University of Pennsylvania, March 7, 1981 (Box 119, Folder 9)
  - Housatonic Valley Association, Annual Meeting, Dubos Lecture, October 17, 1981 (Box 119, Folder 9)
  - Academic Speakers Program, "Celebrations of Life", The University of Tennessee at Martin, 1981 (Box 119, Folder 9)
  - Seventh International Symposium, How Humans Adapt: A Biocultural Odyssey, "Social and Technological Adaptations to the Future", Smithsonian Institution, November 8-12, 1981 (Box 119, Folder 9)
  - University of Brasilia Seminars, "Dubos Na UnB", [text, in Portuguese], 1981 (Box 119, Folder 10)
  - For Spacious Skies National Conference, South Rim of the Grand Canyon, Arizona, May 30-June 1, 1981 (Box 119, Folder 11)
  - Xième Conference Internationale de Gerontologie Sociale, "Mieux vivre pour bien vieillir", [Aging Well Through Living Better], Deauville, France, May 26-28, 1982 (Box 119, Folder 12)
  - SUNY Purchase First Annual René Dubos Lecture, April 25, 1984 (Box 119, Folder 13)
  - American Council on Science and Health, "Perspectives in Cancer Prevention", November 19, 1984 (Box 119, Folder 13)
  - The René Dubos Fellowship Fund Honorary Dinner, "Environmental Regeneration", February 29, 1984 (Box 119, Folder 13)
  - Symposium International: Homme - Santé - Environnement, "L'Esprit de René Dubos ou Les Dangers d'une Approche Fragmentaire en Ecologie", [Man-Health-Environment, The Spirit of René Dubos or Approaching a Fragmentary Ecology] Luxembourg, March 4, 1988 (Box 119, Folder 14)
  - The International Conference on Social Welfare, Social Development in Times of Uncertainty, "Western Modes of Development Under Question", [text], Hong Kong, undated (Box 119, Folder 15)
  - The Distinguished Scientist Lecture Series, Bard College, Annandale-on-Hudson, New York, undated (Box 119, Folder 16)
- (MANUSCRIPTS, TYPESCRIPTS AND GALLEY PROOFS)
  - MS and TS, Untitled, undated (Box 120, Folder 1)
    By Marie-Louise Bonnet [Mrs. René Dubos]. [1917 ?]. In French. Impressionistic narrative set in France During WWI, but with little historical context or fact.
    Pages are not in sequential order, as found.
  - MS, "The Living Past", 1943 (Box 120, Folder 2)
    Essay written by RJD on the anniversary of Marie-Louise Bonnet's death. Dated April 28. In French.
- (MANUSCRIPTS, TYPESCRIPTS AND GALLEY PROOFS)
  - TS, Lecture, 1961 (Box 121, Folder 1)
    "La Santé et la Condition Humaine", [Health and the Human Condition], La Conférence des Sommets, Brussels. In French with annotations, [missing page 31].
  - TS, Lecture I, 1962? (Box 121, Folder 2)
    "Portraits of the Mind".
  - TS, 1965 (Box 121, Folder 3)
    "Life on Earth." With annotations.
  - TS, Untitled, 1970? (Box 121, Folder 4)
    [re Mabel Bright's 25th anniversary at RU. With annotations].
  - TS, Article, 1970 (Box 121, Folder 5)
    Forbes [untitled], September 15.
  - TS, Lecture "Le Prix International de L'Institut de la Vie", [The International Proze of the Institute of Life] November 22. With annotations (Box 121, Folder 6)
  - TS, 1972? (Box 121, Folder 7)
    "Connaissance de la Campagne." With annotations.
  - TS, 1973? (Box 121, Folder 8)
    "Les Professions De Santé et L'Art de Vivre", [Health Professions and the Art of Life]. With annotations.
  - TS, 1973? (Box 121, Folder 9)
    "Sensory Perception and the Museum Experience." With annotations.
  - TS, 1974 (Box 121, Folder 10)
    L'Étre Humain: "Les Choix Qu'il Fait Pour S'adapter en Cerant Son Propre Environnement." With annotations.
  - TS, 1974 (Box 121, Folder 11)
    Foreward to Concepts in Ethology: Animal and Human Behavior by Michael Fox, written by RJD, February. With annotations.
  - TS, Article, 1974 or 1975 (Box 121, Folder 12)
    "The Recycling of (Human) Nature (Only) The Past Has a Future", The Saturday Review. With annotations.
  - TS, Essays, 1975 (Box 121, Folder 13)
    "Reasons for Hope", and "Trend is Not Destiny." With annotations.
  - TS, Lecture, 1976 (Box 121, Folder 14)
    "Determinisme et Responsabilité: Choisir d'Étre Humain" [Opening of the Center for Bioethics, Montreal] September.
  - TS, Lecture, 1977 (Box 121, Folder 15)
    "La Recherche Medicale et L'Avenir de la Medecine", [Medical Research and the Future of Medicine] Sherbrooke. With annotations.
  - TS, 1977 (Box 121, Folder 16)
    "Shelters, Open Spaces, and Adaptations", with annotations.
  - TS, 1977? (Box 121, Folder 17)
    "Environment, Social Choices and Human Development", October.
  - TS, Lecture, 1977 (Box 121, Folder 18)
    "Environmental Design and (New-Style Humanism) Social Choices Countercultures in Architecture".
  - TS, 1977 or 1978? (Box 121, Folder 19)
    "Improvement in Individual Health is Bad for the World's Health" and a review by RJD of "The Ecological Perspective in Social Work Practice by Germain [found together].
  - TS, Lecture, 1978 (Box 121, Folder 20)
    "Les Origines Sociales De la Recherche Medicale" [The Social Determinants of Medical Research]. With annotations.
  - TS, Lecture, 1979 (Box 121, Folder 21)
    "Les Retombes de la Crise Énergétique", July 2. With annotations.
  - TS, Lecture, 1979 (Box 121, Folder 22)
    "Ameliorer La Vie en Economisant L'énergétique" [Better Life Through Less Energy], L'Institut de la Vie, Paris With annotations.
  - TS, 1979 (Box 121, Folder 23)
    "From Wilderness to Farmland and Parkland", August. [Prepared for Land Use Forum, not used. Later adapted for Michigan Quarterly Review, Spring 1980] With Annotations.
  - TS, 1979 (Box 121, Folder 24)
    "Coexistence of Rural and Urban Areas", September 11.
  - TS, Lecture, 1979 (Box 121, Folder 25)
    "A Plea for Community Spirit and Self-Sufficiency", November 9.
  - TS, Article, 1980 (Box 121, Folder 26)
    L"Leader's Article" with minor differences], March 7 re: The René Dubos Center. With annotations.
  - TS, Lecture, 1980 (Box 121, Folder 27)
    "The Future of the Plant Sciences and the Critical Roles of Botanical Gardens and Arboreta", [The Rockefeller University, delivered on October 6 - also dated August].
  - TS [Lecture?], 1980 (Box 121, Folder 28)
    "Homeostasis and Its Failures", [photocopy], with annotations and notes.
  - TS and MS, 1980 (Box 121, Folder 29)
    "Adaptation au Futur", [Adaption to the Future; photocopy] In French.
  - TS, Lecture, 1980 (Box 121, Folder 30)
    "Le Mythe de la Nature", [The Myth of Nature] March. Deauville, June 8. With annotations.
  - TS, Article/Address, 1981 April-May (Box 121, Folder 31)
    "Entering the 21st Century".
  - TS, Lecture, 1981 (Box 121, Folder 32)
    "L'Ecologie Créatice, Symbiose Entre La Terre and L'Humanité, Conférence de la M.G.E.N., Toulouse, July 5. With annotations.
  - TS and MS, 1981? (Box 121, Folder 33)
    "Berthe et André Noufflard Vus par les Dubos", with annotations.
  - TS, Article, 1981 (Box 121, Folder 34)
    N.Y. Times Op Ed, "Creation of New Farmland and Preservation of the Tropical Forest [Creating Farmland Through Science], October 20. With annotations.
  - TS, 1981 (Box 121, Folder 35)
    "Technological and Social Adaptations to the Future" Opening address to "How Humans Adapt: A Biocultural Odyssey", Smithsonian International Symposium, Washington, D.C. November 8-12.
  - TS, 1981 (Box 121, Folder 36)
    Introduction to Japanese Translation of "The White Plague".
  - MS, [Eulogy or Lecture?], [l981?] (Box 121, Folder 37)
    Re: Barbara Ward.
  - TS, Article, 1982 (Box 121, Folder 38)
    "The Socialization of Troubled Teenagers: The Wasted Potential of Adolescents, January.
  - TS, Article/Essay, 1982 (Box 121, Folder 39)
    "Shelters: Their Environmental Conditioning and Social Relevance", for an exhibition at the Katanah Gallery, March 13-May 32. With annotations.
  - TS, Article, 1982 (Box 121, Folder 40)
    "Education For the Celebration of Life: Optimism Despite it All", Teacher's College Record.
  - TS, "A Celebration of Life" - Proposed Television Documentary, 1979? (Box 122, Folder 1)
    Various Sections of TS. With annotations [1978 working title, "So Human and Animal"].
  - TS, "A Celebration of Life" - Proposed Television Documentary, 1979? (Box 122, Folder 2)
    Various sections of TS. With annotations.
  - TS, "A Celebration of Life" - Proposed Television Documentary, 1979? (Box 122, Folder 3)
  - TS, "Celebrations of Life", 1981 (Box 122, Folder 4)
    I. The Humanization of Homo Sapiens. With annotations.
  - TS, "Celebrations of Life", 1981 (Box 122, Folder 5)
    II. The Past, Public Places and Self Discovery. With annotations.
  - TS, "Celebrations of Life", 1981 (Box 122, Folder 6)
    III. Think Globally, Act Locally. With annotations.
  - TS, "Celebrations of Life", 1981 (Box 122, Folder 7)
    IV. Trend Is Not Destiny. With annotations.
  - TS, "Celebrations of Life", 1981 (Box 122, Folder 8)
    V. Material Resources and the Resourcesfulness of Life. With annotations.
  - TS, "Celebrations of Life", 1981 (Box 122, Folder 9)
    VI. Optimism Despite It All. With annotations.
  - TS, "Celebrations of Life", 1981 (Box 123, Folder 1)
    Title page, copyright, table of contents and forward. With annotations.
  - TS, "Celebrations of Life", 1981 (Box 123, Folder 2)
  - TS, "Celebrations of Life", 1981 (Box 123, Folder 3)
    II. The Past, Public Places, and Self-discovery. With annotations.
  - TS, "Celebrations of Life", 1981 (Box 123, Folder 4)
  - TS, "Celebrations of Life", 1981 (Box 123, Folder 5)
    IV. Trend is not Destiny. With annotations.
  - TS, "Celebrations of Life", 1981 (Box 123, Folder 6)
    V. Material Resources and the Resourcefulness of Life. With annotations.
  - TS, "Celebrations of Life", 1981 (Box 123, Folder 7)
    VI. Optimism, Despite It All. With annotations.
  - TS, "Celebrations of Life", 1981 (Box 123, Folder 8)
    Envoi and Index. With annotations.
  - Quest by René Dubos and Jean-Paul Escande
    - TS, "Quest", 1979 (Box 124, Folder 1)
      Title page, ad page, copyright, dedication, preface, and introduction. With annotations.
    - TS, "Quest", 1979 (Box 124, Folder 2)
      Chapter I. René Dubos Conquers the West. With annotations.
    - TS, "Quest", 1979 (Box 124, Folder 3)
      Chapter II. Scientists. With annotations.
    - TS, "Quest", 1979 (Box 124, Folder 4)
      III. Physicians. With annotations.
    - TS, "Quest", 1979 (Box 124, Folder 5)
      IV. ____ and Humanity. With annotations.
    - TS, "Quest", 1979 (Box 124, Folder 6)
      V. René Dubos - No Holds Barred. With annotations.
    - TS, "Quest", 1979 (Box 124, Folder 7)
      Draft pages 14, 8, 15, 15a and 75 - earlier drafts. With annotations.
    - GP, "Quest", 1979-1980 (Box 124, Folder 8)
      With annotations.
    - "Quest", 1979-1980; PP [Page Proof] (Box 124, Folder 9)
- (MANUSCRIPTS AND TYPESCRIPTS)
  [Contains bits and pieces of manuscripts, most written in RJD's hand; incomplete and undated. It is likely that since Dubos wrote his ideas on paper as thoughts came to him, these items possibly represent future ideas for articles or may be earlier forms of his published works].
  - MS, "Adaptation à l'Avenir (au Futur) - Role de la Medecine", [Adaptation to the Future - Role of Medecine], undated (Box 125, Folder 1)
  - MS, "The Global Trotter at Home", undated (Box 125, Folder 2)
  - MS, "The Healing Brain", undated (Box 125, Folder 3)
  - MS, "Joie de Vivre" - in English, undated (Box 125, Folder 4)
  - TS, "La Saga de L'Espèce Humaine", with annotations, undated (Box 125, Folder 5)
  - MS, "Think Globally, Act Locally" and "Trend is Not Destiny", undated (Box 125, Folder 6)
  - TS, "Wilderness and Humanized Nature in America", undated (Box 125, Folder 7)
  - TS, "The Wooing of the Earth", With annotations, [Newman Award], undated (Box 125, Folder 8)
  - MS, Untitled, Incomplete, undated (Box 125, Folder 9)
    [re: adaptation and unemployment.
  - MS, Untitled, Incomplete, undated (Box 125, Folder 10)
    [Adaptations to the future].
  - MS, Untitled, Incomplete, undated (Box 125, Folder 11)
    [re: "The Development of the Person"].
  - MS, Untitled, Incomplete, undated (Box 125, Folder 12)
    [re: "environmental recovery" and "disenchantment with technology"].
  - MS, Untitled, Incomplete, undated (Box 125, Folder 13)
    [re: land use - France and Brazil].
  - MS, Untitled, Incomplete, undated (Box 125, Folder 14)
    ["I twice lectured on environmental and social problems in several cities of Japan and Israel..."].
  - MS, Untitled, Incomplete, undated (Box 125, Folder 15)
    [re: economic development - Japan, Israel, and the Netherlands].
  - MS, Untitled, Incomplete, undated (Box 125, Folder 16)
    [The Global Village, Global Thinking].
  - MS, Untitled, Incomplete, undated (Box 125, Folder 17)
    [re: humankind].
  - MS, Untitled, Incomplete, undated (Box 125, Folder 18)
    [re: human nature].
  - TS, Untitled, Incomplete, undated (Box 125, Folder 19)
    "p. 16" re: Jamaica Bay.
  - MS, Untitled, Incomplete, undated (Box 125, Folder 20)
    [re: pollution and energy].
  - MS, Untitled, Incomplete, undated (Box 125, Folder 21)
    [re: Bertha and tuberculosis] In French.
  - MS, Untitled, Incomplete, undated (Box 125, Folder 22)
    ["In many situations, the faith that heals is thus a medical reality"].
  - MS, Untitled, Incomplete, undated (Box 125, Folder 23)
    ["The anaticapular enzyme was the first antibiotic produced in the laboratory"].
  - MS, Untitled, Incomplete, undated (Box 125, Folder 24)
    Lre: Jean Dubos' response to a conversation which occurred in France].
  - MS, Untitled, Incomplete, undated (Box 125, Folder 25)
    Lre: Hindu Poet, Sir Rabin Dranath Tagore (1861-1941)].
  - TS, Untitled, Incomplete, undated (Box 125, Folder 26)
    [re: "concept of progress"].
  - MS, Index to Unidentified Book, undated (Box 125, Folder 27)
    MS, untitled, Incomplete.
  - One page draft in Dubos' hand re: Concord flight and comment on animal and human life (Box 125, Folder 28)
  - MSS, untitled, incomplete, undated (Box 125, Folder 29)
    Various pieces of MS, found together. Subject matter includes nutrition, human characteristics, adaptation to the future, and the environmental movement.
  - MSS, untitled, incomplete, undated (Box 125, Folder 30)
    Several small notes written by Dubos in English and French.
- (ARTWORK)
  - Stillife, 1961? (Box 126, Folder 1)
    "Memories of Jean's East Window", watercolor and pencil on paper. Unsigned.
  - Portrait, 1967 (Box 126, Folder 2)
    Sketch of R. Dubos, Australia. Unsigned.
  - Portrait, 1976 (Box 126, Folder 3)
    Sketch of R. Dubos by Jon Zahourck. Ink [pen] on paper.
  - Caricature, 1980 (Box 126, Folder 4)
    By Al Hering for "NRDC Amicus (Alice Andrews) ".
  - Informal Portrait, undated (Box 126, Folder 5)
    Dubos in labcoat. Pencil drawn on Board.
  - Portrait, undated (Box 126, Folder 6)
    Sketch of Dubos by Genevieve Noufflard at Garrison, New York [photocopy].
    See also Oversized for Sketch of R. Dubos by Marie-Louise Bonnet and Sketch of Dubos by Constance Burke Schnurr.
- (80th BIRTHDAY CELEBRATION and EXHIBITION)
  - 80th Birthday Celebration, 1981 (Box 127, Folder 1)
    Birthday cards and notes.
  - 80th Birthday Celebration, 1981 (Box 127, Folder 2)
    "Celebrations of Life: A Tribute to René Dubos for his 80th birthday", January 8, 1981 at the New York Hilton. [Program, seating list, sample stationary and envelope, and text of remarks of Dubos].
  - Exhibition. "Humanized Nature", 1981-1982 (Box 127, Folder 3)
- (CORRESPONDENCE)
  [Correspondence is arranged according to the system devised for Boxes 10-24].
  - Ac-Ak, 1978 1987 (Box 128, Folder 1)
  - Ap-Az, 1981 (Box 128, Folder 2)
  - From Marie-Louise Bonnet to R. Dubos, 1940 July 1942 March 25 (Box 128, Folder 3)
  - Bou-Boy, 1984 (Box 128, Folder 4)
  - Br, 1981 (Box 128, Folder 5)
    [See also TS, "Entering the 21st Century", April - May 1981, Box 121, Folder 31].
  - Car, 1967 (Box 128, Folder 6)
  - Cha, 1955 (Box 128, Folder 7)
  - Cou-Coy, 1970 (Box 128, Folder 8)
  - Cr, 1963 1968 (Box 128, Folder 9)
  - Da, 1976 (Box 128, Folder 10)
  - To Adeline Dubos [René J. Dubos's mother], In French, 1952-1953 (Box 128, Folder 11)
  - To and From Dubos, Francis, In French, 1981, undated (Box 128, Folder 12)
  - Dornay, Gabriel [In French], 1981-1982 (Box 128, Folder 13)
  - Ec-Ei, 1960-1961 1963 1965 (Box 128, Folder 14)
  - Es-Ey, 1971 (Box 128, Folder 15)
  - Fi-Fl, 1972 (Box 128, Folder 16)
  - Fo, 1981 (Box 128, Folder 17)
  - Fr, 1968 (Box 128, Folder 18)
  - Graham, Laurie, 1980 (Box 128, Folder 19)
  - Kan-Kav, 1966 1973 (Box 128, Folder 20)
  - Kea-Ken, 1973 (Box 128, Folder 21)
  - Lev, undated (Box 128, Folder 22)
  - Li, 1965 (Box 128, Folder 23)